<chapter xml:id="introduction">
<title> Introduction </title>

The power of scripting to model eclipsing binary stars is becoming more and more important with the fire-hose of data coming our way. What people often don't realize is that, even for case-by-case modeling, scripting proves to be of utmost importance as it offers much more flexibility than the Graphical User Interface (<abbrev>GUI</abbrev>). For example, there is no (ready) way to determine heuristic error estimates of adjusted parameters in the <abbrev>GUI</abbrev>, whereas it takes a handful of script lines to perform heuristic scanning. It is our goal, with this reference manual, to bring PHOEBE's scripting language closer to its users and to explain how to use it to model and solve real-life (well, for as long as binary star modeling is called real life) problems.

<sect1>
<title> What to expect from this document? </title>

<para>
PHOEBE scripting language is a new programming language developed specifically for modeling eclipsing binary stars. The scripter is an interactive interface that "speaks" this language. A user communicates with the program by passing statements that perform particular actions. A set of statements is called a script. Script statements are made of smaller building blocks: directives and commands. This document thoroughly describes all such building blocks, along with their synopsis and lots of examples. This section introduces the rationale behind PHOEBE and lists some prerequisites for running the scripter comfortably. In <xref linkend="general_properties"/> we concentrate on general properties of the scripting language, followed by the discussion on parameter identifiers, user-defined variables and supported types in <xref linkend="identifiers"/>. <xref linkend="arithmetics"/> is dedicated to arithmetic rules and type propagation. Loops and conditionals will be covered in <xref linkend="loops"/>, and basic building blocks that make statements will be thoroughly overviewed in <xref linkend="directives"/> and <xref linkend="commands"/>. To round up the overview, several usage examples will be given in <xref linkend="examples"/>. In <xref linkend="grammar"/> we elaborate on grammatical concepts of the scripting language itself.
</para>

<para>
Along with the description and synopsis, a working example is given for each scripter directive or command. When examples depend on file locations, we shall presume that PHOEBE is run from the the base directory (<filename>phoebe-0.31a/</filename>). If you run PHOEBE from a different directory, simply replace file paths with the ones that correspond to your directory layout.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title> Things you need to know </title>

<para>
The aim of this document is to introduce PHOEBE scripting language as thoroughly as possible. For practical reasons we do not cover the details that are not directly connected with the scripter. Throughout the document we thus assume that the reader is:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem> familiar with basic concepts of eclipsing binary modeling. Although experience using PHOEBE in the GUI mode is recommended, it is not required to follow this document; </listitem>
<listitem> comfortable with handling ASCII files (being able to create, read, write and modify them); </listitem>
<listitem> acquainted with the operating system and knows how to use the command line. </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

</chapter>
